<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-/UVA::IATH/DTD whitman.dtd (Whitman Archive)/EN"
"whitman.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY xxx.00001 PUBLIC "-/UVA::IATH/TEXT (Whitman Archive xxx.00001)/EN"
 "xxx.00001.xml" NDATA xml>
]>
<TEI.2 id="xxx.00264" type="work">
   <relations>
      <workparent entity="xxx.00001">
         <bibl>
            <title>Leaves of Grass</title>
         </bibl>
      </workparent>
   </relations>
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title level="a" type="main">The Sleepers</title>
            <title level="a" type="uniform">Sleepers, The</title>
            <author>Walt Whitman</author>
            <editor>Kenneth M. Price</editor>
            <editor>Ed Folsom</editor>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Work description by</resp>
               <name>Whitman Archive Staff</name>
               <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
               <name>The Walt Whitman Archive Staff</name>
            </respStmt>
            <sponsor>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Iowa</sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</sponsor>
            <funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            <funder>The United States Department of Education</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2003</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <idno>xxx.00264</idno>
            <distributor>The Walt Whitman Archive</distributor>
            <address> 
       <addrLine>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the
        Humanities</addrLine> 
       <addrLine>Alderman Library</addrLine> 
       <addrLine>University of Virginia</addrLine> 
       <addrLine>P.O. Box 400115</addrLine> 
       <addrLine>Charlottesville, VA 22904-4115</addrLine> 
       <addrLine>whitman@jefferson.village.virginia.edu</addrLine> 
      </address>
            <availability>
               <p>Copyright &#xA9; 2003 by Ed Folsom and Kenneth M. Price, all rights reserved.
                  Items in the Archive may be shared in accordance with the Fair Use provisions of
                  U.S. copyright law. Redistribution or republication on other terms, in any medium,
                  requires express written consent from the editors and advance notification of the
                  publisher, The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities. Permission to
                  reproduce the graphic images in this archive has been granted by the owners of the
                  originals for this publication only.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Original</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords>
               <term type="genreForm">Poetry</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="ancillary">
      <body>
         <p>In the 1871 edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass,</hi> Whitman gave this poem the title “The Sleepers,” the title it has come to be known by, and, on the printer’s copy of Whitman’s hand-revised copy of the 1871 edition, the poem underwent its final revisions. In each of the editions of <hi rend="italic">Leaves,</hi> from 1855 through 1881, the poem appeared in a distinctive version, as well as in a changed position in relation to the other poems in the volume. A number of manuscripts predating 1855 contain proto-versions of particular sections of the poem, and some manuscripts contain notes that lead to particular elements in the poem.

The ultimate “descendant” is “The Sleepers” as it appears in the 1881 edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass.</hi> All subsequent reprintings of the poem overseen by Whitman are identical to this one and are in fact printed from the same plates. “The Sleepers” (1881) is the final progeny of what was approximately a thirty-year process of invention, composition, and revision.

The immediate predecessor of “The Sleepers” (1881) is the printed version of “The Sleepers” (1871) as revised by Whitman. This printed version with Whitman’s manuscript revisions, deletions, additions, and corrections, is reprinted in Joel Myerson’s <hi rend="italic">Whitman Archive,</hi> vol. 1, pp. 495-518; the originals are in the Library of Congress. If we follow all of Whitman’s manuscript instructions on this printed 1871 “The Sleepers,” we arrive at the 1881 “The Sleepers,” but the corrected printed copy of “The Sleepers” (1871) allows us to track the decisions Whitman was making, including changes he considered but then decided against (like his initial cancellation of what became Section 5 of the poem, about Washington after “the defeat at Brooklyn”). Whitman’s marked-up copy of “The Sleepers” (1871), then, is a mixed manuscript/printed version that allows us to track the process of revision between the 1871 and 1881 versions of the poem.

The predecessor of this corrected printed 1871 version is the printed 1871 version itself, from <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> (1871 edition). The predecessor of the 1871 printed version is the version in the 1867 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass,</hi> entitled “Sleep-Chasings.”  Its predecessor is the printed version in the 1860 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass</hi> as altered by Whitman in his “Blue Book” working copy of the 1860 <hi rend="italic">Leaves,</hi> now at New York Public Library. Like the corrected 1871 version, this 1860 corrected version becomes the basis for the subsequent printing (in this case the 1867 version). The predecessor of this altered version of the 1860 printing is the actual 1860 edition of the poem, also called “Sleep-Chasings” (though in all caps, instead of small and large caps as in 1867). The predecessor of the 1860 version is the version in the 1856 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass,</hi> called “Night Poem.”  And its predecessor—the printed progenitor of “The Sleepers” (1881)—is the untitled poem in the first edition of Leaves of Grass, beginning “I wander all night in my vision,” the fourth of twelve poems in that edition. Every one of these printed versions of the poem in the different editions of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi> (1855, 1856, 1860, 1867, 1871, and 1881) has elements unique to it, and every edition sets the poem in a singular context, surrounding it each time with a quite different group of poems. 

The 1855 printed version of the poem has numerous manuscript antecedents. The manuscripts closest to the 1855 version of the poem are three fragments now at the University of Virginia. All three are drafts of the “Lucifer” section of the poem, and, while it is not possible to determine which draft came first, it is reasonable to assume that the fragment beginning “I am black a curse” is the earliest, followed by the fragment beginning “Crash Topple down upon her Curse,” followed by the draft that is the closest to the printed version, “I am a hell-name and a Curse.”  It is impossible to tell whether these drafts were revised and re-revised individually or simultaneously (that is, we can’t know whether Whitman came back to an earlier draft after writing a later draft and worked on the earlier one, then the later one, or both at the same time). 

These three fragments descend from a three-page section of Whitman’s early notebook, “Talbot Wilson,” now in the Library of Congress. This notebook contains what appear to be Whitman’s earliest notes toward the 1855 <hi rend="italic">Leaves of Grass,</hi> and the relevant three-page section begins “I am a curse.”  This notebook section seems to be the manuscript progenitor of the Lucifer section of the poem, although there are several other manuscripts where Whitman deals with Lucifer; these other manuscripts are relevant to the origins of the poem, even if they are not direct progenitors. These manuscripts include “Religions—Gods” (Boston Public Library), “Pictures” (an early, proto-Leaves unpublished poem, MS at Yale), and “Poem Incarnating the Mind” (Library of Congress), a manuscript that complicates things even further, because it demonstrates that “Lucifer” was once part of Whitman’s original drafts for what became the fugitive slave section in “Song of Myself,” and the cancelled line about Lucifer in this manuscript indicates that Whitman early on in the writing process was dividing the slave material between “Song of Myself” and “The Sleepers.”

The “Talbot Wilson” notebook contains other images, lines, and passages that anticipate the poem, in addition to the Lucifer-related lines indicated above. One key line in the poem (“The twisted skull waits, the watery or rotten blood waits”) is first drafted in this notebook (“A twisted skull, and blood watery or rotten by ancestry or gluttony, or rum or bad disorders,--they are the darkness toward which the plant will not grow, although its seed lies waiting for ages”). So the “Talbot Wilson” notebook is clearly one of the main progenitors for the poem.

Two other early Whitman notebooks, both in the Library of Congress, anticipate the 1855 version of the poem. Both these notebooks are in prose: that is, they do not draft poetic lines but rather develop ideas more discursively. The first, “Diphthong,” contains Whitman’s initial struggles toward the image of the whale as force of retribution, an image that finally appears in the Lucifer section of the poem. This notebook places the image clearly and fully in the context of slavery (“It is as logical to take the life or property of some poor fellow for his inferiority or color, as it is to take his personal liberty.—Beware the flukes of the whale. He is slow and sleepy—but when he moves, his lightest touch is death”). The second notebook, “No doubt the efflux of the soul,” is a longer one (24 leaves) that lays out the philosophical ideas that generate the poem and produces some of the key images in the first section of the poem (“Cache! And Cache again! All over the earth, and in the heavens that swathe the earth, and in the waters of the sea.—They do their jobs well; those journeymen divine. Only from the Poet they can hide nothing and would not if they could”). 

Whitman was, therefore, generating different parts of his poem in at least three different notebooks—working out in one notebook the imagery in trial poetic lines, and working out in the other two the main ideas in prose. These notebooks, as far as we can tell, are the ur-writing for the poem that eventually becomes “The Sleepers.”

There are several holes in the genealogy. Clearly, Whitman used a copy of each edition of <hi rend="italic">Leaves</hi> to mark up and revise for the next edition, but we only know of two such marked-up editions (the 1860 “Blue Book” and the disbound 1871 edition—along with a disbound copy of <hi rend="italic">Two Rivulets</hi>—that is now scattered in various archives); there no doubt once existed a marked-up 1856 <hi rend="italic">Leave</hi>s and a marked-up 1867 edition. These marked-up editions trace the evolution of the poem as it moves from one edition to the next. The other hole consists of the missing manuscripts and notebooks: We just happen to know of the specific manuscripts discussed above that led to several discrete sections of the poem, but there must have once been manuscripts that similarly led to the other sections as well.

</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
