<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<teiHeader xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>Ulysses. An electronic version of the critical and synoptic edition.</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <editionStmt>
            <edition>Electronic version</edition>
        </editionStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <p>This electronic edition was created as part of a <term>Diplomarbeit</term> for the<rs>Technische Universität München</rs>.
                <emph>Note that the text and the edition are copyrighted and may not be distributed freely.</emph>
                The copyright notices of the printed edition still apply where applicable:</p>
            <p>Draft texts, revisional material, and reading text of <title>Ulysses</title> ©<date>1984</date>, The Trustees of the Estate of James Joyce</p>
            <p>Presentation of Genetic Synopsis, Notes and Afterword ©<date>1984</date>, Hans Walter Gabler</p>
            <p>The compiler of the electronic version, from his side, agrees to all non-commercial use of his work.</p>
        </publicationStmt>
        <notesStmt>
            <note>This electronic edition was first automatically converted from the
                TUSTEP files used for preparation of the printed edition; necessary corrections and additional tagging
                were done by hand afterwards.</note>
            <note>The electronic edition comprises the continuous manuscript text as on the left hand pages of the
                printed edition (this also implies the reading text, as on the right hand pages), the emendatory
                footnotes, the historical collation and the textual notes in the Appendix. The date information from
                table 1 on page 1913 is also incorporated, so are some data from the bibliography relevant to the historical
                collation. The preface, afterword, and the additional information in the bibliography and table 1 and 2 in
                the appendix are not included.</note>
        </notesStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="gab">
                <monogr>
                    <author>James Joyce</author>
                    <editor role="editor">Hans Walter Gabler</editor>
                    <title type="main">Ulysses</title>
                    <title type="subordinate">A Critical and Synoptic Edition</title>
                    <edition>Second Impression</edition>
                    <imprint>
                        <publisher>Garland Publishing Inc.</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <date>1986</date>
                    </imprint>
                </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <listWit>
                <witness xml:id="e22">
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>James Joyce</author>
                            <title>Ulysses</title>
                            <edition>First edition</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Shakespeare and Company</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <date>1922</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="e26">
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>James Joyce</author>
                            <title>Ulysses</title>
                            <edition>Second edition, set from the first</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Shakespeare and Company</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <date>1926</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="e32">
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>James Joyce</author>
                            <title>Ulysses</title>
                            <edition>Fourth edition, set from the second</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>The Odyssey Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Hamburg</pubPlace>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <pubPlace>Bologna</pubPlace>
                                <date>1932</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="e36">
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>James Joyce</author>
                            <title>Ulysses</title>
                            <edition>Seventh edition (first impression), set from the fourth</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>The Bodley Head</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <date>1936</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="e37">
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>James Joyce</author>
                            <title>Ulysses</title>
                            <edition>Seventh edition (second impression, with authorial corrections), set from the seventh (first impression)</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>The Bodley Head</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <date>1937</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="e60">
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>James Joyce</author>
                            <title>Ulysses</title>
                            <edition>Eighth edition, set from the seventh (first impression)</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>The Bodley Head</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <date>1960</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="e61">
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>James Joyce</author>
                            <title>Ulysses</title>
                            <edition>Ninth edition, set from the eighth</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Random House</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <date>1961</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.ROS" n="R"><date when="1918">fair copy (Rosenbach Manuscript)</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.B" n="B"><date when="1918">final working draft revision</date> as typed beyond final working draft state represented in fair copy; lost</witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.C" n="C"><date when="1918">typescript overlay</date>, partially extant</witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.D" n="D"><date when="1921">typescript overlay</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.1" n="1"><date from="1921-08-03" to="1921-08-27">proof</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.2" n="2"><date from="1921-08-18" to="1921-09-17">proof</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.3" n="3"><date from="1921-09-21" to="1921-10-05">proof</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.4" n="4"><date from="1921-09-27" to="1921-10-08">proof</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.5" n="5"><date from="1921-10-01" to="1921-10-12">proof</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.6" n="6"><date from="1921-10-07" to="1921-10-12">proof</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.7" n="7"><date when="1921-10-12">proof</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL8.8" n="8"><date when="1922-02-02">first edition</date></witness>
                <witness xml:id="LVL.GAB"><date when="1986">the reading text of the Gabler Edition</date></witness>
            </listWit>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <projectDesc>
            <p>This electronic edition was prepared as part of a computer science <term>Diplomarbeit</term> for the<rs>Technische Universität München</rs>.
                It is an attempt to remodel the information structure of the printed Gabler edition of <title>Ulysses</title>
                explicitly in SGML, as closely as possible to the TEI P3 standard.</p>
            <p>With the time and resources given, the bulk of the SGML text files had to be generated automatically from
                the electronic documents used in the preparation of the printed edition. This hopefully gives a very
                correct text, but in many places gives crude and/or bad tagging.</p>
            <p>The tagging applied shall serve two main purposes: To generate a TEI-compatible version of some
                particular level of the text, notably the reading text as established by the Gabler edition, and to
                create an online critical edition that allows more intuitive access to the information structures
                available in the Gabler edition.</p>
        </projectDesc>
        <editorialDecl>
            <quotation form="data" marks="all">
                <p>Quotations are not tagged explicitly. Direct speech in the main text is marked exclusively with em
                    dashes at the beginning of a new paragraph. What graphically looks like left and right single quotes
                    in the main text are apostrophes and left single quotes used in contracted Irish names as <q>M‘Coy</q>
                    and in similar forms of transcription (e.g. from Hebrew). These are coded as entity references to
                    the standard ISO entities apos and lsquo. Quotations in the notes use single or double quotes.
                </p>
            </quotation>
            <hyphenation eol="none">
                <p>End-of-line hyphenation and soft hyphens introduced for typographic reasons in the computer files for
                    the printed edition is discarded or represented by soft hyphen entities (shy). Explicit hyphens in
                    the text can be considered as hard hyphens in compound words. Hyphenation information related to
                    Joyce's manuscripts that is provided explicitly in the printed edition is marked with word break
                    tags (wbreak).</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <segmentation>
                <p>The main text is separated in three divisions, representing the three parts of the book. Each part is
                    subdivided into episodes, eighteen altogether. The episodes 7 (Aeolus), 10 (Wandering Rocks) and
                    17 (Ithaca) are again subdivided into their obvious elements.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <stdVals>
                <p>Where dates are given as attribute values, they are either of the form <q>1904</q> to denote a whole
                    year, or of the form <q>1904-06-16</q> to denote a particular day (the sixteenth of June 1904 in this case).
                    There are <q>date</q> and <q>daterange</q> elements without content where the date ist to be derived
                    from the attributes.</p>
            </stdVals>
        </editorialDecl>
        <refsDecl>
            <p>Two canonical reference systems are coded into the main text: There are the page and line-per-page
                numbers of the left-hand pages (the synoptic pages) of the printed edition, which are coded with
                <q>pb</q> and <q>lb</q> milestones with the <q>ed</q> attribute set to <q>syn</q> (for<q>synoptic</q>).
                And there are the lines-per-chapter numbers serving as a standard reference to the reading text of the
                Gabler edition, which are coded with <q>lb</q> tags with attribute <q>ed</q> set to <q>gab</q>
                (for<q>Gabler</q>). To complete these references, one needs the chapter number given in the <q>n</q>
                attribute of the episode level <q>div</q> elements.</p>
            <p>It may be unfortunate, but there are also <q>lb</q> tags in the notes that are not part of a reference
                system; they indicate a relevant line break in the source manuscript instead.</p>
        </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
            <language xml:id="ENG" ident="en">The main language of the text is English, although a lot of the words are
                not  Standard English but new coinages that often also mimic other languages.
                In the current version of the SGML transcription, no distinction of languages is made — all italics are
                just tagged as highlighted.</language>
        </langUsage>
        <handNotes/>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change who="#rischer" when="1996-11-14">SGML version frozen from the last automatic conversion. Incomplete and faulty in details.</change>
        <change who="#rischer" when="1996-11-28">Pushed and pulled through the needle's eye: it parses. Corrected some obvious conversion blunders, but not too systematically.</change>
        <change who="#rischer" when="1997-02-01">I have remodelled the file structure for the appendix slightly and added the layout specs for
                exceptional cases. I did a lot of manual editing at critical spots and have rerun the conversion for
                systematic blunders. The whole thing is a lot better now, but still needs testing and improvement. The
                tag set documentation is not completed.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>